hey push students let's cover everything
you need to know for the exam for period
4 before we start print out the speed
review sheet to help you follow along
with this video it's free and you can
find the link in the description below
right now look at period 4 Circle any
people events vocab things that you
might not quite remember that you know
you need to focus on as we review Once
you're confident that you've mastered a
topic you can check it off and move on
to the next all right here we go Thomas
Jefferson's election is called the
Revolution of 1800 because it's the
first peaceful transfer of power from
one party to the next for the Young
Jefferson faced several foreign policy
challenges as president including the
Louisiana Purchase running with the
barbery Pirates and the Embargo Act
Jefferson was conflicted on the
Louisiana Purchase because the
Constitution did not strictly give the
president the power to purchase the
territory ultimately he agreed to the
purchase because it would further his
ideals of an agrarian nation and it
doubled the size of the United States
lwis and Clark with the help of saak
jaia explored the territory the barbar
Pirates incident also conflicted with
Jefferson's strict interpretation of the
Constitution because he paid a tribute
to release American hostages and
expanded the US Navy to fight the pirate
in Tripoli also when Britain and France
tried to interfere with American
neutrality during the Napoleonic Wars
Jefferson responded by passing the
Embargo Act of 1807 this damaged the US
economy and Jefferson's administration
which also caused him to step down after
two terms James Madison was elected in
1808 his first term was focused on the
economy following the failed Embargo Act
in the expiration of the National Bank
Charter but his second term was consumed
with the War of 1812 also known as the
second war of independence America went
to war with Great Britain because of
continued impressment of American
Sailors and because Britain continued to
supply natives on the Frontier with
weapons young warhawks in Congress like
Henry Clay and John C Calhoun supported
the war while Democratic Republicans
from the south and the West voted in
favor of the war Federalists opposed it
this led to the failed Hartford
Convention where Federalists held a
secret meeting attempting to limit The
Growing Power of the democratic
Republican party two events from this
war that you want to know are the Battle
of Baltimore where the star Bengal
Banner was written and the burning of
the White House by the British the war
concluded with the Treaty of gent in
1814 the British agreed to end
impressment and abandon the forts in the
Northwest Territory and both sides
agreed to help end the African slave
news of this treaty however did not
reach Andrew Jackson who led the
Americans into victory at the Battle of
New Orleans after the war was over after
the war America entered a period of
patriotism and nationalism known as the
Era of Good Feelings America experienced
economic prosperity and political Unity
with an era of democratic Republican
leadership James Andro the third
Democratic Republican president also
served two terms he is most known for
the passage of the Monroe Doctrine which
reaffirmed America's isolation as
foreign policy demanding Europe stay out
of the Western Hemisphere but the vast
differences between the northern and
southern economies continued to increase
sexualism Clays Missouri Compromise
attempted to ease these tensions
Missouri entered the Union as a slave
state and Main as a free state helping
to maintain the balance in Congress this
also created the 3630 line to help
determine whether new States would allow
for slavery clay also proposed the
American system which included the
development of a national economy
through government funded infrastructure
a protective tariff for American
manufacturing and the Second National
Bank the Era of Good Feelings came to an
end in 1824 following the election of
John Quincy Adams in what became known
as the corrupt bargain Andrew Jackson
felt the House of Representatives had
cheated him leading to a split in the
party part this coincided with the
expansion of white male suffrage which
resulted in jackon and Democrats
electing him in 1828 as the Common Man
president Jackson's Administration was
dominated by controversy including the
Nullification Crisis surrounding the
Tariff of Abominations the national bank
and the Indian Removal Act his political
opponents accused Jackson of being a
tyrant as he ignored Supreme Court
decisions and excessively vetoed bills
their hatred of Jackson led to the
formation of the Wake party now let's
look at the Marshall Court John Marshall
was a federalist judge appointed by Don
Adams he served as chief justice for 34
years in pretty much any decision of the
Marshall Court expanded the power of the
federal government over the states cases
under Marshall include barbar B Madison
which established judicial review mull
Maryland which upheld the
constitutionality of the National Bank
and granted Congress implied powers and
Gibbons vogon which ruled the federal
government could control interstate
trade rall also ruled in wer be Georgia
that the federal government did not have
the right to regulate Native American
land the decision Andrew Jackson ignored
the Industrial Revolution also took
place during period 4 it's often
referred to as the market Revolution
it's characterized by Innovation and
industrialization Northern cities
especially along waterways saw the
development of textile factories while
the West saw the mechanization of
Agriculture with the steel plow and the
mechanical reaper and the invention of
the cotton gen made cotton King of the
Southern economy this also included a
transportation Revolution the
development of the steam engine led to
Innovations like railroads and
steamboats the national economy boomed
from the introduction of interchangeable
parts and the telegraph connected
Regional economies all of these changed
America's Workforce through the use of
unskilled labor many of these jobs were
filled by women children and immigrants
who were paid low wages four young women
often worked in factories like the low
Mills but returned home when they got
married however women in the upper class
and new middle class did not work
reaffirming women's roles in the
household starting in the 1820s large
numbers of Irish and German immigrants
came to America the Irish escaping the
Potato Famine settled predominantly in
northeastern cities and took jobs in
factories or building railroads the
Germans who were escaping political
turmoil often settled in the midwest
many Americans resented the influx of
immigrants for white men living in
cities felt groups like The Irish were
taking jobs from them Protestants also
resented the increasing number of
Catholics this all led to the creation
of the Native as know nothing party the
second grade awakening increased Church
attendance and inspired social and moral
reforms the Abolitionist Movement called
for the end of slavery leading
abolitionists like William Lloyd
Garrison published The Liberator and
founded the American anti-slavery
Society Frederick Douglas who was
formerly enslaved or his personal
narrative illustrating the cruelties of
enslavement the women's rights movement
met at the sen Cals convention led by
Elizabeth Katie Stanton and lukisha mo
they drafted the Declaration of
Sentiments calling for equality tral
reforms include Temperance education
prison reform and mental hospital
America also saw the development of
utopian communities romanticism and
transcendentalism transcendentalists
like Henry David throw called for civil
disobedience and Ralph wo Emerson wrote
about the truth found in nature so what
does this look like on exam day or
causation you could be asked about the
development of a national identity or
the effects of the market Revolution
comparison questions will center around
nationalism versus sexualism or the
differences in the various reform
movements for change in continuity
you'll likely see questions about
changes in political parties or changes
in the role of women check out the aush
ultimate review packet for more help
we've got timeline study guides and
Essay practice check out the link in the
description below to get a free preview
and if you think this video is helpful
like And subscribe